<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Down by the River</title>
    <atom:link href="http://www.downbytheriver.us/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"></atom:link>
    <link>http://www.downbytheriver.us</link>
    <description>Van -&gt; RV Conversion. Live and work down by the river.</description>
    <pubDate>Sun, 31 Mar 2013 18:00:00 -0600</pubDate>
    <generator>Wintersmith - https://github.com/jnordberg/wintersmith</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <item>
      <title>How to Install Click Flooring in a van</title>
      <link>http://www.downbytheriver.us/articles/2013-04-01_Install-Click-Flooring-in-a-Van/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 31 Mar 2013 18:00:00 -0600</pubDate>
      <guid isPermaLink="true">http://www.downbytheriver.us/articles/2013-04-01_Install-Click-Flooring-in-a-Van/</guid>
      <author></author>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Installing flooring in a van is the first step (wish I’d known when I started :) to conversion to an RV. I chose laminate click flooring because it’s easy to clean, durable, and I love a bright wood look.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I built this at TechShop in San Francisco. Living in the city I don’t have room for tools and the wood shop there made cutting the flooring to size a piece of cake.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;more&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-plan-layers-&quot;&gt;The Plan (Layers)&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Click flooring   (Laminate/compressed wood)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Underlayment     (1/4” Cork)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Moisture Barrier (Plastic)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Flattener        (Reflectix to fill ridges in floor)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Bare, prepared van metal&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/articles/2013-04-01_Install-Click-Flooring-in-a-Van/van-floor-layers.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Sketch of Layers&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;prepare-metal&quot;&gt;Prepare Metal&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Prepare the van interior by cleaning, sanding out any rust, and repaiting. You aren’t going to see the actual van floor again (hopefully ever), so don’t leave any rust around to melt your floor out from under you. I also chose to paint with a layer of sound dampening paint like Lizardskin but this is optional.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/articles/2013-04-01_Install-Click-Flooring-in-a-Van/diy-lizardskin-on-van.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;DIY Lizardskin on Van floor&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;fill-gaps-to-level-floor&quot;&gt;Fill Gaps to Level Floor&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The floor of most vans has 1/2-1/4” ridges that help make the floor more stable. I wanted to bring this up to a level height so that an installed floor would me more stable. Also, the more insulation the better :)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Reflectix is a good choice because it’s made of plastic so it can’t hold moisture or rot. It will provide a small amount of radiant heat insulation (good if you park over a hot parking lot).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To fill the gaps, I simply cut it into strips and taped it down. Having a buddy to help makes it go really fast.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/articles/2013-04-01_Install-Click-Flooring-in-a-Van/reflectix-to-fill-van-floor-grooves.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Reflectix in Van Floor&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;moisture-barrier&quot;&gt;Moisture Barrier&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Because you’re gonna put a floor down, and because all humans exude humidity, and especially because I spill things and make a mess, you need a moisture barrier. This keeps moisture off your van’s metal floor.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Buy a cheap roll of the stuff at home depot. It’s just heavy duty plastic. You attach it with silicone and keep a water tight seal away from your van’s metal floor.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Pretty easy stuff there.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/articles/2013-04-01_Install-Click-Flooring-in-a-Van/moisture-barrier-on-van-floor.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Moisture Barrier on Van Floor&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;underlayment&quot;&gt;Underlayment&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Underlayment keeps your click flooring from scooting around too much, vibrating, and is your chance to insulte under the floor. You can get cheap felt stuff, but I suggest cork because it’s all natural and provides great sound proofing and some insulative properties.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Cork is easy to cut with a sharp razor blade and doesn’t need to get glued down or anything, so it’s pretty easy to put in.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/articles/2013-04-01_Install-Click-Flooring-in-a-Van/cork-underlayment-for-van-floor.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Cork Underlayment for Van Floor&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;click-flooring&quot;&gt;Click Flooring&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once all the prep layers are in, you can cut the floor to size and install it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I suggest you start with the furthest back corner and build your way out. I made this more difficult on myself than needed by having an L shaped couch already attached to the floor. Don’t do this to yourself unless you really like cutting small shapes into planks of your flooring.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The click flooring is pretty easy to install, just cut them to fit your space and press them into place. A rubber mallet helps a lot.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/articles/2013-04-01_Install-Click-Flooring-in-a-Van/click-flooring-in-van.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Click Flooring Installed In Van&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Van Floor Moisture Barrier and Underlayment</title>
      <link>http://www.downbytheriver.us/articles/2013-01-31_Install-Moisture-Barrier-and-Underlayment-In-Your-Van/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 30 Jan 2013 17:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
      <guid isPermaLink="true">http://www.downbytheriver.us/articles/2013-01-31_Install-Moisture-Barrier-and-Underlayment-In-Your-Van/</guid>
      <author></author>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Converting a van to an RV requires a good moisture barrier to prevent rust and a good underlayment to insulate, reduce noise, and prevent vibration.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;more&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The floor of the ford e350 is grooved, to provide stuctural stability I think, or to help match with a future installed disco ball. The floor I ultimately want to put in is hardwood, so I needed to install an underlayment and moisture barrier.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The order of layers is:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Van floor  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Something to fill the grooves  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Cut through holes  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Moisture barrier  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Cork Underlayment&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;filling-the-grooves&quot;&gt;Filling the Grooves&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Grooves were filled with strips of Reflectix because of the minor insulation benefit they’d provide and because they don’t retain any moisture. They don’t level out the grooves completely since they aren’t very compression resistant but they’re better than nothing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Reflectix cuts easily with scissors and masochistically with a razor blade. You can see in the photos that the L shape frame would have been better if it were not in the way at this point.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/articles/2013-01-31_Install-Moisture-Barrier-and-Underlayment-In-Your-Van/1-buddy-grooves.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Install it with a friend&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/articles/2013-01-31_Install-Moisture-Barrier-and-Underlayment-In-Your-Van/2-groove-detail.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Reflectix GrooveDetail&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/articles/2013-01-31_Install-Moisture-Barrier-and-Underlayment-In-Your-Van/3-groove-detail.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Groove Detail&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;cut-through-holes&quot;&gt;Cut through holes&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I knew I needed to get holes through the bottom of the vehicle for a plumbing drain–not the usual way, but if I’m just draining rinse water, I don’t see a problem. I cut a hole using a spade shaped hole cutting wood bit. This took forever to do, but the PVC fit was perfect. I hammered in facing pieces with a rubber mallet and secured with liquid nails for hold and butyl putty for waterproofing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This fitting will later let me attach PVC plumbing to it so I can drain my sink outdoors when appropriate.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I want under-mounted leisure batteries, but I wasn’t sure what through holes I needed for these so I’ll have to lift up the floor to install these later.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/articles/2013-01-31_Install-Moisture-Barrier-and-Underlayment-In-Your-Van/4-plumbing.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Seal through hole&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/articles/2013-01-31_Install-Moisture-Barrier-and-Underlayment-In-Your-Van/5-pvc-plumbing.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;PVC Drain with Cap&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;moisture-barrier&quot;&gt;Moisture Barrier&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Moisture barrier is some black plastic made for the purpose from a home supply store. Installed by laying it right over the Reflectix, cut to fit in the van, and secured around the edges with silicone.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ignore the framing in these pictures and the Reflectix on the walls–that got in the way and should have been done after the whole floor was installed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/articles/2013-01-31_Install-Moisture-Barrier-and-Underlayment-In-Your-Van/6-moisture-barrier.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Moisture Barrier&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/articles/2013-01-31_Install-Moisture-Barrier-and-Underlayment-In-Your-Van/7-moisture-barrier-detail.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Moisture Barrier Detail&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;cork-underlayment&quot;&gt;Cork Underlayment&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I used cork for underlayment, sound proofing, and some small amount of insulation because:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Cork doesn’t outgas chemicals like foam does&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It’s easy to work with&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can cut cork with a razor blade. I just cut it and dry fit all the pieces. The temporary floor I have installed (not pictured), sits right over floating cork without any slipping problems, so I think the floating-fit is a fine installation technique here. The cork is pretty curled up so I tried to weight it down flat with wood scraps and heavy objects like cans of soup, art history books, and feather pillows.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/articles/2013-01-31_Install-Moisture-Barrier-and-Underlayment-In-Your-Van/8-cork-underlayment.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Cork Underlayment&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/articles/2013-01-31_Install-Moisture-Barrier-and-Underlayment-In-Your-Van/9-cork-underlayment-cutting.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Cutting Cork Underlayment&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/articles/2013-01-31_Install-Moisture-Barrier-and-Underlayment-In-Your-Van/10-cork-underlayment-detail.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Cork Underlayment Detail&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/articles/2013-01-31_Install-Moisture-Barrier-and-Underlayment-In-Your-Van/11-cork-underlayment.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Cork Underlayment&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Frame and Insulate Your Van Walls</title>
      <link>http://www.downbytheriver.us/articles/2013-01-31_Frame-and-Insulate-Your-Van-Walls/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 30 Jan 2013 17:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
      <guid isPermaLink="true">http://www.downbytheriver.us/articles/2013-01-31_Frame-and-Insulate-Your-Van-Walls/</guid>
      <author></author>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Insulation keeps your van cool in the summer and warm in the winter. Insulating a van interior means carefully considering balancing aspects like interior space, moisture retention, toxic chemicals, and insulative properties.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;more&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The walls were framed horizontally at 23” apart so that insulation could run horizontally and minimal framing would be needed. I did an outside layer of Reflectix, held in place with 2x2 framing studs, and stapled the insulation to those.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;steps-&quot;&gt;Steps:&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Stuff Reflectix and loose fill insulation into gaps and holes&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Dry fit reflectix&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Dry fit framing&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Screw framing into van wall through the Reflectix&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Add needed wall anchors&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Install insulation&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;stuff-reflectix-loose-fill-insulation-into-gaps&quot;&gt;Stuff Reflectix &amp;amp; Loose-fill Insulation into Gaps&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My van was full of holes in the walls, the doors, everywhere. It is very like political arguments in this way. I dry fit Reflectix into as many of the spaces as I could. Reflectix bounces radiant heat out, so it’s the first layer. After that I stuffed in loose fill insulation. I used cellulose, which is natural and has no nasty nasty chemicals, but I got nervous about it retaining moisture so I bagged it in freezer bags first and shoved those into as many gaps as I could. Remaining holes I stuffed with Polyester fiberfill which should not retain moisture as much and could get into tiny gaps.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/articles/2013-01-31_Frame-and-Insulate-Your-Van-Walls/1-reflectix-in-walls.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Reflectix in van walls&quot;&gt;
Get reflectix in as many gaps as you can
&lt;img src=&quot;/articles/2013-01-31_Frame-and-Insulate-Your-Van-Walls/2-loose-fill.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Loose Fill Cellulose Insulation&quot;&gt;
Cellulose is toxin-free and is a fair insulator. Retains moisture though.
&lt;img src=&quot;/articles/2013-01-31_Frame-and-Insulate-Your-Van-Walls/3-van-walls-stuffed.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;asdf&quot;&gt;
Van walls stuffed with cellulose in freezer backs and polyester stuffing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;attach-framing-and-reflectix&quot;&gt;Attach Framing and Reflectix&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I cut Reflectix to fit the whole van and fit it in place using clamps, and cut the framing I would need. Then I attached the framing to the van walls using self tapping stainless steel screws, which actually don’t work well through wood–you still have to two step it, since it’s trying to pull through the wood while it’s tapping the hole for the sheet metal.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I framed around the skylights at this point, too, anticipating where the insulation would go.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What I really liked about this installation method is the reflectix was all attached without any adhesives or glues, so there’s no possiblity of toxic outgassing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/articles/2013-01-31_Frame-and-Insulate-Your-Van-Walls/4-reflectix-on-van-ceiling.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Reflectix on Ceiling&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/articles/2013-01-31_Frame-and-Insulate-Your-Van-Walls/5-reflectix-on-van-walls.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Reflectix on Van Walls&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/articles/2013-01-31_Frame-and-Insulate-Your-Van-Walls/6-reflectix-in-van-interior.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Reflectix on Van Interior&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;wall-anchors&quot;&gt;Wall Anchors&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I attached some anchors to the walls to help stabilize the furniture. I think I’ll want more in the future but I added the ones I knew about. Getting them behind the reflectix wasn’t tough–just cut notches where the attachment points need to get.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/articles/2013-01-31_Frame-and-Insulate-Your-Van-Walls/7-framing-attachment-behind-reflectix.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Framing Attachment&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;install-insulation&quot;&gt;Install Insulation&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I thought and read a lot about insulation. There are many options:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Fiberglass (itchy to install, usually bound with Formaldehyde)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Denim (moisture retaining, not locally available)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Cellulose (loose fill likely to settle)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Kingspan rigid foam boards (shows toxic outgassing for years)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/articles/2013-01-31_Frame-and-Insulate-Your-Van-Walls/9-insulation-product.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Ecotouch Insulation&quot;&gt;
I ultimately went with a new fiberglass type called ‘Ecotouch’ which isn’t bound with Formaldehyde because it was locally available, had good r-value, wouldn’t retain moisture, and was non-toxic as best as I could tell.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/articles/2013-01-31_Frame-and-Insulate-Your-Van-Walls/8-me-installing-van-insulation.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Installation Outfit&quot;&gt;
Still itchy to install though. We suited up and stapled insulation against the framing and wedged it into the remaining door panels.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/articles/2013-01-31_Frame-and-Insulate-Your-Van-Walls/10-hold-insulation-against-ceiling.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Insulation held with tension against fiberglass ceiling&quot;&gt;
I had some denim available and used it in the above-cabin compartment where fiberglass was too thick. Most of the roof insulation was tension fit using 2x1s wedged against the existing steel framing.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Build a Folding Bed Platform in Your Van</title>
      <link>http://www.downbytheriver.us/articles/2013-01-31_Build-a-Folding-Bed-Platform-in-Your-Van/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 30 Jan 2013 17:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
      <guid isPermaLink="true">http://www.downbytheriver.us/articles/2013-01-31_Build-a-Folding-Bed-Platform-in-Your-Van/</guid>
      <author></author>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I wanted to build a bed that can fold into a couch.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;more&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I wanted to build a bed that can fold into a couch.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The couch is designed to be L-shaped, with a folding section that extends to make a bed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The basic frame was built using 2x2s and 2x4s. The vertical supports were bolted thrrough the floor of the van using lag bolts from underneath and huge fender washers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The wall attachments use galvanized lumber hangers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/articles/2013-01-31_Build-a-Folding-Bed-Platform-in-Your-Van/1-framing-basic.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Framing_basic&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The joists for the bed are velcro attached 2x2s. This was an easy way to make them removable, but is not very stable. It worked for our 3 week trip, but I’d like to improve it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The couch back interlocks with the other 2x2s and so folds in an unconventional way. I think it will work, but I can’t be sure until I get foam in place for the bed and matress.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/articles/2013-01-31_Build-a-Folding-Bed-Platform-in-Your-Van/3-framing-fold-up.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Framing_fold_up&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/articles/2013-01-31_Build-a-Folding-Bed-Platform-in-Your-Van/2-framing-fold-down.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Framing_fold_down&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We used it as a matress platform and it’s great for that, but I’m not sure how convertabile it is at this point.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/articles/2013-01-31_Build-a-Folding-Bed-Platform-in-Your-Van/4-framing-with-mattress.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;With Matress&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;update&quot;&gt;Update&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The folding system didn’t work well. I’ve removed the folding portion. The point where the extended platform meets the far support gets a lot of stress, and the manner of folding means cargo can’t really be under the couch. I’m working on a different way to do this.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Add Sound and Heat Resistance to Your Van with DIY Lizardskin</title>
      <link>http://www.downbytheriver.us/articles/2013-01-30_Add-Sound-and-Heat-Resitance-to-Your-Car-With-DIY-Lizardskin-and-Dynamat-Alternative/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 29 Jan 2013 17:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
      <guid isPermaLink="true">http://www.downbytheriver.us/articles/2013-01-30_Add-Sound-and-Heat-Resitance-to-Your-Car-With-DIY-Lizardskin-and-Dynamat-Alternative/</guid>
      <author></author>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Prepared a cargo van for heat/sound proofing and rust prevention.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;more&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After emptying out the van, the next step was to clean the interior, paint it with a heat/sound proof coating, and add a few pieces of sound deadening material.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Interior Cleaning&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I used a product called TSP, Trisodium Phosphate, to prepare the van for painting. It seems to be what people recommend. I think it worked ok, but the paint does still scrape off easily. Could be that I used latex paint, but I do wish I’d rough sanded the walls a bit. I think it’ll still stick ok, since the paint will be protected behind layers of insulation and paneling later. This stuff is pretty scary looking, so I wore gloves and a mask and stuff.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/articles/2013-01-30_Add-Sound-and-Heat-Resitance-to-Your-Car-With-DIY-Lizardskin-and-Dynamat-Alternative/1-tsp-cleaning-prep.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;TSP Cleaning Agent&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Heat &amp;amp; Sound Blocking Paint&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lizardskin is an expensive product that hot rod builders use to deaden sound and block some heat transfer. Folks online say that you can make your own substitute by mixing ceramic microbeads with paint. I bought my paint from the Wal-mart mismade color section my beads from Wicks Aircraft Supply. Most folks seem to recommend a 1 gallon of paint to 1lb of microbeads ratio. That’s what I did. If the TSP was scary, microbeads were from a vampire laser dinosaur horror film. The stuff looks like a liquid and a powder at once. I bought the full Darth Vader mask for this stuff. Takes forever to mix up. I mixed it and painted it all over the inside.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/articles/2013-01-30_Add-Sound-and-Heat-Resitance-to-Your-Car-With-DIY-Lizardskin-and-Dynamat-Alternative/3-doors.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Doors&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/articles/2013-01-30_Add-Sound-and-Heat-Resitance-to-Your-Car-With-DIY-Lizardskin-and-Dynamat-Alternative/5-interior-van-painted.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Wet_paint&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/articles/2013-01-30_Add-Sound-and-Heat-Resitance-to-Your-Car-With-DIY-Lizardskin-and-Dynamat-Alternative/2-door.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Door&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/articles/2013-01-30_Add-Sound-and-Heat-Resitance-to-Your-Car-With-DIY-Lizardskin-and-Dynamat-Alternative/4-mixing-diy-lizard-skin.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Mixing&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/articles/2013-01-30_Add-Sound-and-Heat-Resitance-to-Your-Car-With-DIY-Lizardskin-and-Dynamat-Alternative/4-me-mask.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Respirator for Mixing Paint&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.camperize.com/ceramic-paint-microbeads.html&quot;&gt;http://www.camperize.com/ceramic-paint-microbeads.html&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.collegeparktuning.com/showthread.php?t=2712&quot;&gt;http://www.collegeparktuning.com/showthread.php?t=2712&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.hotrodders.com/forum/alternative-lizard-skin-103610-13.html&quot;&gt;http://www.hotrodders.com/forum/alternative-lizard-skin-103610-13.html&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sound Deadening Tiles&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To begin to deaden sound, one needs to stop the metal from vibrating. Dinamat is the brand name of this material. Folks seem to say that roofing products more or less do the same thing. They’re asphalt based and outgas nasty petroleum based stuff, so I limited my use of them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Based on advice from the source below, I believe that I only need about 25% coverage for these sound deadening tiles to be effective. (judging now, with everything else in place, sound suppression seems very good)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I tried to put them inside the doors and on the largest flat pieces of sheet metal.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/articles/2013-01-30_Add-Sound-and-Heat-Resitance-to-Your-Car-With-DIY-Lizardskin-and-Dynamat-Alternative/7-interior-sound-deadening.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Deadened&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/articles/2013-01-30_Add-Sound-and-Heat-Resitance-to-Your-Car-With-DIY-Lizardskin-and-Dynamat-Alternative/6-paint-and-sound-deadening.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Dead_doors&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/articles/2013-01-30_Add-Sound-and-Heat-Resitance-to-Your-Car-With-DIY-Lizardskin-and-Dynamat-Alternative/8-sound-deadening-product.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Product&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.sounddeadenershowdown.com/&quot;&gt;http://www.sounddeadenershowdown.com/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Prepare Your Van for a 3 Week Cross-Country Road Trip</title>
      <link>http://www.downbytheriver.us/articles/2013-01-30_Prepare-Your-Van-For-a-3-Week-Cross-Country-Tip/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 29 Jan 2013 17:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
      <guid isPermaLink="true">http://www.downbytheriver.us/articles/2013-01-30_Prepare-Your-Van-For-a-3-Week-Cross-Country-Tip/</guid>
      <author></author>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I did a flurry of work on the van in preparation for a 3 week cross-crountry road trip. It started with a lot of drawing, as many things do if you’re trying to avoid real work, or if you hire a design school graduate. Graph paper was the best medium for this kind of drawing and I’d suggest it for you and your children’s children.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;more&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I did a flurry of work on the van in preparation for a 3 week cross-crountry road trip. It started with a lot of drawing, as many things do if you’re trying to avoid real work, or if you hire a design school graduate. Graph paper was the best medium for this kind of drawing and I’d suggest it for you and your children’s children.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/articles/2013-01-30_Prepare-Your-Van-For-a-3-Week-Cross-Country-Tip/1-planning.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Planning&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After drawing, visiting home improvment stores, drawing some more, and settling on a plan, I had to look at the current state of the van and empty it out.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Cleaning House&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The existing bed was not attached to the van chassis and was a solid piece. It didn’t do the cool couch-to-bed folding that I wanted out for a real professional rubbertramping bedcouch. It was also extremely… dynamic… in the event of a rapid, collision-style stop.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/articles/2013-01-30_Prepare-Your-Van-For-a-3-Week-Cross-Country-Tip/2-matress.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Original Matress and frame&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/articles/2013-01-30_Prepare-Your-Van-For-a-3-Week-Cross-Country-Tip/3-original-bedframe.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Original Bedframe&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Emptied Out:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/articles/2013-01-30_Prepare-Your-Van-For-a-3-Week-Cross-Country-Tip/4-empty-dirty-van.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Empty&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/articles/2013-01-30_Prepare-Your-Van-For-a-3-Week-Cross-Country-Tip/5-empty-dirtyish-van.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Totally_bare&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Initial Framing&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After clearing out the van, I did some inital framing of the furniture.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I set up an outdoor workshop:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/articles/2013-01-30_Prepare-Your-Van-For-a-3-Week-Cross-Country-Tip/6-workshop.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Workshop&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then I framed the L shape for the convertable bed/couch. I decided to frame in 2x2s, which was a good decision I think. 2x4s then became a good size for vertical supports. Building the furniture frame at this point was mostly a waste of time since the floor and wall framing should happen first, but I didn’t know that when I started. It was nice to see the drawing turn into something real, but I found it got in the way while I was working on the floor and walls later. The mounting points and style had to change later as the floor added height and the wall framing suggested some different ideas for attaching to the wall.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/articles/2013-01-30_Prepare-Your-Van-For-a-3-Week-Cross-Country-Tip/7-couch-bed-frame.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Couch Bed Frame in Van&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/articles/2013-01-30_Prepare-Your-Van-For-a-3-Week-Cross-Country-Tip/8-fancy-joint.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&amp;#39;Fancy&amp;#39; 2x2 Joint&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/articles/2013-01-30_Prepare-Your-Van-For-a-3-Week-Cross-Country-Tip/9-couch-detail.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Couch frame detail&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/articles/2013-01-30_Prepare-Your-Van-For-a-3-Week-Cross-Country-Tip/10-wall-attachments.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Wall attachments from frame to van&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>How to Build a Wooden Bedframe in a Van</title>
      <link>http://www.downbytheriver.us/articles/2011-09-25_Build-a-Simple-Wooden-Bedframe-In-a-Van/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 24 Sep 2010 18:00:00 -0600</pubDate>
      <guid isPermaLink="true">http://www.downbytheriver.us/articles/2011-09-25_Build-a-Simple-Wooden-Bedframe-In-a-Van/</guid>
      <author></author>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In preparation for a move from PA to FL, I need both a sleeping area and some storage for the things I’m moving in the van.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;more&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have some ambitious plans for building out the interior. This planning amounts to fancy procrastination and it has delayed the building of any kind of bed. I have been rolling around with a queen size mattress on the floor of the van for the past year or so. It’s effective and comfortable, but a huge waste of space.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am about to relocate from &lt;a href=&quot;http://maps.google.com/maps?q=philadelphia+pa+to+panama+city+fl&quot;&gt;Philadelphia to Panama City&lt;/a&gt;, so I need both a sleeping area and some storage for the things I’m moving in the van.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/articles/2011-09-25_Build-a-Simple-Wooden-Bedframe-In-a-Van/1-trip-map.png&quot; alt=&quot;Trip Map&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My solution was a quick and easy wooden bedframe designed specifically to be an inch taller than the gray storage bins I buy at Walmart.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Cost for all supplies was $74.57. Time invested was something like 5 hours. It could have been done cheaper using wood braces and lots of 45 degree mitre cuts, but I had already packed my power tools so I was working with a hand saw. The metal joining brackets I used made this much easier to build, though more expensive.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Steps&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;1: Sketch out a plan. This was done at Home Depot in the lumber section.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/articles/2011-09-25_Build-a-Simple-Wooden-Bedframe-In-a-Van/2-plan.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Sketches&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;2: Build Rectangle. This could be done outside the van. If I had put legs on it, it wouldn’t have fit through the door, so I had to build the rest inside the van.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/articles/2011-09-25_Build-a-Simple-Wooden-Bedframe-In-a-Van/3-build-frame.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Outside&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;3: Build the Rest. The metal brackets made this an easy build–it was almost as easy as building with lego.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/articles/2011-09-25_Build-a-Simple-Wooden-Bedframe-In-a-Van/4-corner-brace.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Corner&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/articles/2011-09-25_Build-a-Simple-Wooden-Bedframe-In-a-Van/5-angle-brace.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Legbrace&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/articles/2011-09-25_Build-a-Simple-Wooden-Bedframe-In-a-Van/6-double-brace.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Supportbeam&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;4: Result&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/articles/2011-09-25_Build-a-Simple-Wooden-Bedframe-In-a-Van/7-finished-bed-frame-in-van.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Complete Wooden Bed Frame in Van&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>How to Install Vents in a Fiberglass Roof</title>
      <link>http://www.downbytheriver.us/articles/2010-08-14_How-to-Install-Vents-in-a-Fiberglass-Van-Roof/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 18 Jun 2010 18:00:00 -0600</pubDate>
      <guid isPermaLink="true">http://www.downbytheriver.us/articles/2010-08-14_How-to-Install-Vents-in-a-Fiberglass-Van-Roof/</guid>
      <author></author>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I finally cut into the roof today…&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;more&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-plan&quot;&gt;The Plan&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I finally cut into the roof today. I threw all my stuff up on the high top: foam padding, drill, marker, mask, vent trim to outline the shape… Then I climbed up and got nervous. How do I know where in the interior this is going to come down?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So I changed plans. I got inside the van, marked out where I was going to put the van, got the drill all set up, took a deep breath, and started drilling. Hot plastic flying everywhere (it was a mess), and finally a hole punches through. It’s dark. Not bright, like the sky. I get a light and take a look.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;6 inches of air space between me and another fiberglass panel. I knew the roof was some kind of sandwich construction but I thought they’d be more efficient about it. I can’t line up two holes with 6” of space between them. So i cut a bigger hole. Now I can see what’s going on. And it sucks. There’s insulation, wiring for the roof lights, steel reinforcement (!). Not making my vent installation job easy. So I tape up the hole I cut out and quit for the day.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Next day, I come back and I decide I’m going to see if i can just rip out the inner roof.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So I do.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That… was dramatic. Made a big impact. I think I’ll be able to make better use of space now (the old inner roof wasted tons of space above the driver’s compartment), but it’s a total mess. Foil face jute, steel crossmembers everywhere…&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I guess I’m finishing the roof now.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here’s the new plan:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Install roof vents (since the roof is curved this will involve some kind of fabrication [bondo?])&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Paint interior w/ insulative paint&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Install side window&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Frame interior (small wood braces to tack paneling to and give the insulation some room&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Insulate (foil faced jute?)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Panel the interior (I found a nice looking bamboo paneling, and I’m thinking thin carpet for the roof)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Build/Install Bed and cabinet system out of pipe or t-slotted aluminum extrusion&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-execution&quot;&gt;The Execution&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is a step by step description of installing aftermarket/eBay roof vents in a camper van with a fiberglass high top roof. The vents are nice because heat rises and this way you can let it out. I learned most of these methods from different internet sources (linked at the bottom), but there was no good central place with lots of pictures, so I thought I’d make one. Hope this helps, feel free to leave questions in the comments.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;step-1-make-a-template&quot;&gt;Step 1: Make a Template&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I started by making a template out of cardboard that matched the size of the hole I wanted to cut in the roof. The best way I found was to trace the plastic trim piece (the part that actually drops through the roof), then cut out the result. I was going to skip making templates but I’m so glad I didn’t. It made the process much easier.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/articles/2010-08-14_How-to-Install-Vents-in-a-Fiberglass-Van-Roof/1-template-roof-vent.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Roof Vent Template&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;step-2-mark-the-cut-on-the-inside-of-the-roof&quot;&gt;Step 2: Mark the Cut on the Inside of the Roof&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Just trace around the template&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/articles/2010-08-14_How-to-Install-Vents-in-a-Fiberglass-Van-Roof/2-trace-template.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Traced Template on Roof&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;step-3-build-wooden-frames&quot;&gt;Step 3: Build Wooden Frames&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The inner dimension of the frame should match the size of the hole you’ll cut. The wood frames give the vent something to screw in to–the fiberglass isn’t really enough.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/articles/2010-08-14_How-to-Install-Vents-in-a-Fiberglass-Van-Roof/3-build-wooden-frame.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Build Wooden Frame for Vent&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;step-4-attach-the-wooden-frames-to-the-roof&quot;&gt;Step 4: Attach the Wooden Frames to the Roof&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This was actually pretty futile. I used a liquid nails knock off and didn’t want it to offgas too much so I used it lightly. It was useful to make sure the fit was right, but these kept falling off when the drilling and cutting started. Oh–it was also useful because I cut the round corners with a doorknob hole drillbit, so it was easy to mark the right center starting point with these frames in place.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/articles/2010-08-14_How-to-Install-Vents-in-a-Fiberglass-Van-Roof/4-attach-wood-frame-fiberglass-roof.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Attach Frame to Fiberglass Roof&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;step-5-make-the-first-cut&quot;&gt;Step 5: Make the First Cut&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With the wood frames in place, mark all the center points for your drilling. I used a drill bit meant for doing doorknobs, and it worked great. Just get the outside flush with both corners, and drill a little intil the center bites in enough to leave a mark. Do this for all four corners. Then start really cutting on whatever corner you think is the ugliest. The fiberglass is a mess, so wear clothes you’ll throw away and a dust mask. The wood frames started falling apart at this point, but it was OK since all the corner locations were marked.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/articles/2010-08-14_How-to-Install-Vents-in-a-Fiberglass-Van-Roof/5-make-first-cut-in-fiberglass-roof.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Make the First Cut in Your Fiberglass Roof&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;step-6-finish-the-corner-cuts&quot;&gt;Step 6: Finish the Corner Cuts&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finish the other three corner cuts (hopefully you’ve marked them accurately). Then draw straight lines on the outside of the roof between each corner. This will help you keep the jigsaw straight. You could try and do the straight cuts from inside, but I didn’t want to try doing that upside-down.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/articles/2010-08-14_How-to-Install-Vents-in-a-Fiberglass-Van-Roof/6-cut-round-corners-in-fiberglass.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Finish the Corner Cuts&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;step-7-make-the-straight-cuts&quot;&gt;Step 7: Make the Straight Cuts&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Using a jigsaw and a metal cutting blade (what the Home Depot guy recommended for fiberglass), make straight cuts between the corner holes. The construction of the vents gives you plenty of wiggle room, but I still tried to keep the cuts as straight as I could.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/articles/2010-08-14_How-to-Install-Vents-in-a-Fiberglass-Van-Roof/7-straight-cuts-in-fiberglass.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Whole shape cut out&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;step-8-test-fit-your-cut&quot;&gt;Step 8: Test Fit Your Cut&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is the moment of truth. Hope you cut the hole accurtely and drop the vent in from the top. Also, a major concern for me was the slope of the roof. I picked the flattest place I could to install the vent, but as you can see in the picture, there’s still a big difference in the gap’s size as the slope of the roof changes. Because the gap difference was large, I agonized for a while over whether I wanted to use bondo to flatten the mating surface or not. I finally decided to leave it as is and seal it directly to the roof.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/articles/2010-08-14_How-to-Install-Vents-in-a-Fiberglass-Van-Roof/8-dry-fit-vent-in-roof.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Dry Fit Vent in Fiberglass Roof&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;step-9-use-butyl-tape-to-seal-the-vent&quot;&gt;Step 9: Use Butyl Tape to Seal the Vent&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This stuff is wonderful, easy to work with, and forgiving. It never hardens, and waterproofs completely. Love it for this purpose. Grab a roll of Butyl tape from Amazon or an RV supply store. Then just peel off the adhesive and stick it to the vent. (it’ll be stringy like chewed gum if it’s hot out, so leave the roll in the fridge for an hour or so if it’s being a pain). I used extra layers of Butyl where the vent had a larger gap to accomodate the roof’s slope. Just tape all four sides and then smush the vent down into place. If the fit looks alright, start to screw the vent down, right through the Butyl. Once this is done, you should have squeezed out lots of extra Butyl tape and have a nice fit on your roof vent. (the picture shows this on the 2nd vent. I installed 2, don’t let that confuse you–same process)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Butyl Tape Source:&lt;br&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.amazon.com/United-States-R-011B-Butyl-Seal/dp/B000BQUPYE/ref=pd_cp_hi_1&quot;&gt;http://www.amazon.com/United-States-R-011B-Butyl-Seal/dp/B000BQUPYE/ref=pd_cp…&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/articles/2010-08-14_How-to-Install-Vents-in-a-Fiberglass-Van-Roof/9a-seal-vent-to-roof-with-butyl.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Vents sealed with Butyl&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/articles/2010-08-14_How-to-Install-Vents-in-a-Fiberglass-Van-Roof/9b-seal-vent-to-roof-with-butyl.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;One Vent sealed with Butyl&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;step-10-clean-up-the-excess-butyl&quot;&gt;Step 10: Clean Up the Excess Butyl&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Use a plastic knife with the seratted edge filed off to clean up the excess butyl tape and give your install a nice smooth look. (thanks for the tip, random internet stranger!). The plastic knife does the job pretty well. I’m sure there’s a fancier tool available if you like being fancy. Maybe you’ll get lucky and it’ll come with a free martini glass.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/articles/2010-08-14_How-to-Install-Vents-in-a-Fiberglass-Van-Roof/10-remove-excess-butyl-putty.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Remove Excess Butyl Putty&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;step-11-seal-the-screw-holes&quot;&gt;Step 11: Seal the Screw Holes&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(requisite screw holes giggity) Just go over the top of the screw holes with a little bit of non-silicone based sealant. I used Dyco C-10 Flow Seal. Some internet person (in the sources below) said it was great, and I found it to work very well, too. You can buy it here:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.amazon.com/White-C-10-Flow-Leveling-Caulk/dp/B0009N4J6E/ref=sr_1_1?ie=UTF8&amp;amp;s=hi&amp;amp;qid=1281829420&amp;amp;sr=1-1&quot;&gt;http://www.amazon.com/White-C-10-Flow-Leveling-Caulk/dp/B0009N4J6E/ref=sr_1_1…&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’m not sure this step is even necessary, since the screws go in to Butyl anyway, but if the internet tells me to do something, it’s hard to resist. Anyway, it has worked well and I’d do it again. (oh boy, another giggity opportunity)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/articles/2010-08-14_How-to-Install-Vents-in-a-Fiberglass-Van-Roof/11-seal-screw-holes.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Seal Screw Holes&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;appendix-a-the-final-appearance-from-the-inside&quot;&gt;Appendix A: The Final Appearance from the Inside&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I suppose “final” is relative–I haven’t paneled or otherwised finished the interior. But this is what it looks like.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/articles/2010-08-14_How-to-Install-Vents-in-a-Fiberglass-Van-Roof/12-interior-of-roof-vent.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Interior View&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;appendix-b-wrap-up&quot;&gt;Appendix B: Wrap Up&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So that’s all there was to it. Really not as bad as I was expecting. Overall, I’d just suggest measuring very carefully, cutting slowly, and making sure you have the right materials prepared before you cut the first hole. I was very cautious about cutting into the roof of my van, so I read &lt;em&gt;a lot&lt;/em&gt; before starting. The best sources I listed below. I hope this helps someone else.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sources:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://rv-roadtrips.thefuntimesguide.com/2008/10/rv_roof_vent.php&quot;&gt;http://rv-roadtrips.thefuntimesguide.com/2008/10/rv_roof_vent.php&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://rvtravel.com/blog/lowtech/2007/04/its-putty-tape-time.html&quot;&gt;http://rvtravel.com/blog/lowtech/2007/04/its-putty-tape-time.html&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.sunlineclub.com/forums/f71/replacing-roof-vents-101-with-pics-8922.html&quot;&gt;http://www.sunlineclub.com/forums/f71/replacing-roof-vents-101-with-pics-8922…&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.fiberglassrv.com/forums/f55/butyl-tape-silicone-and-sealing-24715.html&quot;&gt;http://www.fiberglassrv.com/forums/f55/butyl-tape-silicone-and-sealing-24715….&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.plustape.com/BK/index.htm&quot;&gt;http://www.plustape.com/BK/index.htm&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=YMru54UY6Aw?wmode=transparent&quot;&gt;http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=YMru54UY6Aw?wmode=transparent&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;appendix-c-2-years-later&quot;&gt;Appendix C: 2 Years Later&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It’s been 2 years since I’ve installed these. They haven’t leaked a bit and seem to be holding up great. This method worked great, highly recommended.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Van Interior Prep and Rust Prevention</title>
      <link>http://www.downbytheriver.us/articles/2010-05-31_Van-Interior-Prep-and-Rust-Prevention/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 30 May 2010 18:00:00 -0600</pubDate>
      <guid isPermaLink="true">http://www.downbytheriver.us/articles/2010-05-31_Van-Interior-Prep-and-Rust-Prevention/</guid>
      <author></author>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;How I prepped the interior of a cargo van for RV conversion.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;more&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Removed old cargo management system and divider wall&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Removed plywood floor&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Removed rust and screws from the interior floor with sandpaper, wire brushed, a grinder fitted with a flap sanding disc (this was awesomely effective)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Painted with Rustoleum’s White Clean Metal Primer&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Mockup of a Van Furniture Layout</title>
      <link>http://www.downbytheriver.us/articles/2010-05-19_Mockup-of-A-Van-Build/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 May 2010 18:00:00 -0600</pubDate>
      <guid isPermaLink="true">http://www.downbytheriver.us/articles/2010-05-19_Mockup-of-A-Van-Build/</guid>
      <author></author>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I planned and drew a lot while trying to figure out how to lay out the interior of the van, but sometimes you have to see it in the space. The best I could do what cardboard boxes to prototype the layout in real space.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;more&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/articles/2010-05-19_Mockup-of-A-Van-Build/furniture-mockup-1.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Furniture Mockup&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The bench to the left. The couch/bed structure is L shaped.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/articles/2010-05-19_Mockup-of-A-Van-Build/furniture-mockup-2.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Furniture Mockup&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Rear view of the L shaped bench and fake sink/heater/closet&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>How to Select a Van for RV Conversion</title>
      <link>http://www.downbytheriver.us/articles/2010-05-06_How-to-Buy-a-Van-for-RV-Conversion/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 05 May 2010 18:00:00 -0600</pubDate>
      <guid isPermaLink="true">http://www.downbytheriver.us/articles/2010-05-06_How-to-Buy-a-Van-for-RV-Conversion/</guid>
      <author></author>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The first step in the process is buying a van, and after a year of looking, planning, and hem-hawing, I did it.I found a 2006 Ford e350 on ebay for $5000 so I scooped it up.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;more&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/articles/2010-05-06_How-to-Buy-a-Van-for-RV-Conversion/ford-e350-high-top.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;My Van&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first step in the process is buying a van, and after a year of looking, planning, and hem-hawing, I did it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I found a 2006 Ford e350 on ebay for $5000 so I scooped it up.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I was leaning towards the sprinter chassis for it’s integrated high top and superior gas mileage, but when I worked out the cost savings for the gas mileage difference it didn’t make up for how much more expensive a sprinter would have been.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I figured that with an average of 300 miles traveled per week and gas prices of $3.25, I’d only be saving $1230 a year driving the sprinter. And to get a sprinter I’d be paying probably $10,000 total, it would have more miles on it, and the parts and repairs would be more expensive.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So I’m happy with the decision and feel after driving this for a few days and working on the interior a bit that the e350 will be a fine chassis to build on.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Selecting Safe and Warm Van Insulation</title>
      <link>http://www.downbytheriver.us/articles/2010-05-02_Selecting-Safe-and-Warm-Van-Insulation/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 01 May 2010 18:00:00 -0600</pubDate>
      <guid isPermaLink="true">http://www.downbytheriver.us/articles/2010-05-02_Selecting-Safe-and-Warm-Van-Insulation/</guid>
      <author></author>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I am considering a few things for my insulation:
Staying cool in the summer, staying warm on chilly nights, not taking away too much interior space, and not offgassing dangerous chemicals.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;more&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It turns out to be hard to find safety data for insulation when used in a very enclosed space like a van.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After doing some reading, it seems like three layers will be practical, effective, and not too expensive to do.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First will be a paint mixed with ceramic beads. A brand name version of this is called Lizard Skin, and it’s supposed to have good insulating properties and does not take up any space inside the van, which is great. This should deaden sound a little bit, keep heat out in the summer, and keep heat in in the winter.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The second layer is a foil face bubble wrap, name brand Reflectix. This is supposed to be great for keeping heat out in the summer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The final layer I haven’t decided on. I think a Jute would be safest in terms of offgassing, but I haven’t ruled out a polystyrene wrapped fiberglass.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sources for Van Insulation Info:&lt;br&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://camperize.com/ceramic-paint-microbeads.html&quot;&gt;http://camperize.com/ceramic-paint-microbeads.html&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.camperize.com/bubble.html&quot;&gt;http://www.hotrodders.com/forum/alternative-lizard-skin-103610.html&lt;br&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.camperize.com/bubble.html&quot;&gt;http://www.camperize.com/bubble.html&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>